{"tossups": [{"question": "One member of this political party had an affair with Georgianna Cavendish and helped craft a document that outlawed slavery in the British Empire. The Earl Grey was a member of this party, which formalized under Charles James Fox. Its power diminished as it entered into a coalition with William Gladstone\u2019s Liberal Party. For the point, name this political party led by William Pitt the Elder and Robert Walpole, which rivaled the Conservatives for dominance in 18th century Britain.", "answer": "<b> Whig</b> Party", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Stagings of this play in the 1950s at Luttringhausen and San Quentin prisons are the subject of the documentary<em> The Impossible Itself</em>. A character in this play confuses a turnip for a carrot, standing near a single tree. In its final act, Pozzo is led on a leash by his slave Lucky. Each act of this play ends with a messenger boy assuring the protagonists that the title character will arrive soon, though he never does. For the point, name this play featuring Vladimir and Estragon, written by Samuel Beckett.", "answer": "<b> Waiting for Godot</b> (accept En<b> attendant Godot</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This country attempted to rid itself of communist sympathizers in its Plan Lazo. Alberto Camargo served as the first leader of this country\u2019s National Front, which was comprised of Liberal and Conservative party factions that had earlier fought the Thousand Days War. The assassination of Jorge Eli\u00b4ecer Gait\u00b4an contributed to the outbreak of La Violencia in this country, and its more recent troubles include the kidnapping of Ingrid Betancourt by FARC operatives. For the point, name this oft-troubled South American nation with capital at Bogota.", "answer": "<b> Colombia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In this election year, one campaign noted that \u201cthis afternoon, 6,500 young men and women will be married.\u201d In a debate during this election year, one candidate stated that he was \u201cnot going to exploit, for political purposes, my opponent\u2019s youth and inexperience.\u201d Earlier in this year, the platform of Gary Hart was criticized using the Wendy\u2019s slogan \u201cWhere\u2019s the beef?\u201d The campaign of the winning candidate in this election included the \u201cMorning in America\u201d TV commercial. Minnesota was the only state won by Walter Mondale in, for the point, which presidential election, a landslide re-election victory for Ronald Reagan?", "answer": "Presidential Election of<b> 1984</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One end of Liverpool\u2019s Anfield Stadium was named for its similarity to a battleground in this war. Dead bodies were removed from the battlefield of Spion Kop by stretcher-bearers led by Mohandas Gandhi in this war. Redvers Bullers was disgraced during the Black Week in this war, in which his three attempts to relieve Colenso, Kimberley, and Mafeking all failed. The Treaty of Vereeniging ended this war, which was partially caused by the Jameson raid. For the point, name this war between the British and Dutch settlers in South Africa.", "answer": "Second Anglo-<b>Boer</b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Colonel John Ohmer disguised an entire aircraft factory in this city as a suburban area. The shelling of Ellwood led to widespread paranoia and a \u201cbattle\u201d over this city that consisted of anti-aircraft guns shooting at a perceived enemy air raid. A riot in this city began when the \u201cVengeance Squad\u201d sought out <em>pachucos</em> wearing distinctive broad-shouldered, long-coated clothing. For the point, name this city where American servicemen attacked Mexicans in the Zoot Suit Riots.", "answer": "<b> L</b>os<b> A</b>ngeles", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this event, one person pleaded with his attackers to \u201crespect these grey hairs.\u201d After hearing of this event, Phillip II was said to have laughed for the only time on record. Pope Gregory XIII sent Charles IX a golden rose following the murder of the aforementioned Gaspard de Coligny [koh-lih-nee] during this event, which was probably ordered by Catherine d\u2019Medici and took place shortly after Margaret of Anjou\u2019s marriage to Henry of Navarre. For the point, name this 1572 slaughter of Huguenots in Paris.", "answer": "<b> St. Bartholomew\u2019s Day Massacre</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One ruler performed this action after witnessing a monk called Poppo hold a red-hot iron without getting burned. Another ruler who performed this action shoved a snake with a hot poker down Raud the Strong\u2019s throat for refusing to perform this action. The Jelling runestones commemorate this action, which was performed by the kings Harald Bluetooth and Olaf Tryggvason. For the point, name this action that involved abandoning a religion that worshipped Odin and Thor in favor of a religion that worships Jesus.", "answer": "<b> converting</b> to<b> Christianity</b> (accept equivalents; accept more specific things like<b> getting baptized</b>; prompt on converting from Norse paganism) (14) The territories exchanged at the end of this conflict were further defined in the \u201cTreaty of Peace and Friendship.\u201d One side raised funds for this conflict through the tax collecting expedition of Patricio Lynch, and it opened with one side occupying the port of Antofagasta. The<em> Esmeralda</em> was sunk by the <em>Huascar</em> in this conflict, which was ended through the Treaty of Ancon. The Atacama Desert\u2019s reserves of guano and saltpeter were a major cause of, for the point, what 1880s conflict in which Bolivia was defeated by Chile and lost access to an ocean? ANSWER: War of the<b> Pacific</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This monarch lost the Duchy of Parma to Spain in the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle. This ruler was influenced by Jewish courtier Abraham Theben and sent physician Gerard van Swieten to investigate reports of vampires. This monarch allied with Louis XV in a deal arranged by her minister, Wenzel Anton von Kaunitz, in the Diplomatic Revolution. Salic Law threatened the legitimacy of this monarch\u2019s rule, leading her father, Charles VI, to pass a Pragmatic Sanction. For the point, name this Austrian Empress who lost the War of the Austrian Succession.", "answer": "<b> Maria Theresa</b> of Austria", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "J.D. Verhoeven\u2019s study of this material questions whether vanadium impurities led to its characteristic appearance. This ultra-high-carbon material was produced from wootz in a way that naturally formed carbon nanotubes. This shatter-resistant metal with a mottled finish was used in sword manufacturing until its production method was lost in the 18th century. For the point, name this type of steel produced in India but named for a Middle Eastern city where Crusaders encountered it.", "answer": "<b> Damascus steel</b>", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {}, {"question": "Michel Aoun\u2019s forces surrendered at this city\u2019s Presidential Palace but were executed in the October 13 massacre. Elie Hobeika\u2019s forces carried out the Sabra and Shatila refugee massacres in this city. During a 1975 to 1990 civil war, this city\u2019s Western Muslim and Eastern Christian neighborhoods were divided by the Green Line. In 2005, Rafic Hariri, the former Prime Minister of this capital city\u2019s country, was assassinated, sparking a non-violent revolution that demanded the withdrawal of Syrian troops from this city. The Cedar Revolution broke out in, for the point, what capital of Lebanon?", "answer": "<b> Beirut</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Samuel Sturgis failed to trap these people, who only lost one man in attacking David Perry at Cottonwood soon before withdrawing at Clearwater. This group included Ollokot and Looking Glass, who both died at the Battle of Bear Paw. In surrendering to Oliver Howard and Nelson Miles, the leader of this group declared that his \u201cheart is sick and sad\u201d and he \u201cwill fight no more forever\u201d. For the point, name this tribe of the Pacific Northwest that attempted to go to Canada in 1877 under the leadership of Chief Joseph.", "answer": "<b> Nez Perce</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Liwa Sub-Prefecture on the shores of this lake is a major center of natron extraction. Yedina people, also known as the Buduma, or \u201cPeople of the Reeds,\u201d inhabit the many islands of this lake. The Jama\u2019are and Hadejia Rivers, tributaries of this lake, have both been heavily dammed, which has partly led to this lake\u2019s contraction of over 95%, though a larger factor of that contraction has been irrigation projects that have rapidly dried up the Chari River. For the point, name this African lake that shares its name with a country with capital at N\u2019Djamena.", "answer": "Lake<b> Chad</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Theodore Roosevelt was angered by this man\u2019s decision to dissent in the breakup of the Northern Securities Company. This man\u2019s opinion in a case involving Silverthorne Lumber established the doctrine of \u201cfruit from the poisonous tree.\u201d<em> Abrams v. US</em> featured the use of this \u201cGreat Dissenter\u2019s\u201d \u201cclear and present danger\u201d standard, as did a 1919 case concerning draft dodging. For the point, name this Supreme Court justice who argued that the First Amendment does not allow one to shout \u201cFire!\u201d in a crowded theater in his unanimous opinion to<em> Schenck v. US</em>.", "answer": "Oliver Wendell<b> Holmes</b>, Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A period of domination by the Theophylacti family in this city was known as the saeculum obscurum, or Rule of the Harlots. Olimpia Aldobrandini was the heir to a family fortune in this city, which passed to her husband, Camilio Pamphili. Benvenuto Cellini defended this city during the War of the League of Cognac, though it was captured and sacked by forces loyal to Emperor Charles V. This city\u2019s Aurelian Walls were breached on the Vente Settembre by Piedmont-Sardinia, resulting in the capital of a new country being moved here from Florence. For the point, name this capital of Italy.", "answer": "<b> Rome</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In this city, a woman who gave birth to a deformed baby, Mary Dyer, was executed in 1660. This city is depicted in<em> The Fruits of Arbitrary Power</em>, which inspired another engraving that shows Captain Preston commanding his troops to fire. A mob in this city attacked the mansion of Governor Thomas Hutchinson in 1765. Crispus Attucks died in this city, with his killers capably defended by John Adams. For the point, what city was the site of a March 1770 \u201cmassacre\u201d of civilians by British troops?", "answer": "<b> Boston</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Joe Hockey became this country\u2019s Ambassador to the United States in early 2016, having resigned as this country\u2019s treasurer in September 2015. The same month, Julie Bishop survived as Deputy Leader of this country\u2019s Liberal Party in its second leadership spill in seven months, which gave this country its fifth Prime Minister in five years. For the point, name this country, formerly led by Julia Gillard, where, in 2015, Malcolm Turnbull replaced Tony Abbott as Prime Minister.", "answer": "<b> Australia</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In 2014, the first Fields Medal awarded to a descendant of this country was given for that man\u2019s work on the geometry of numbers and the rank of elliptic curves. Another mathematician from this country gave the sine function its original name, jya, while another gave a formula generalizing Heron\u2019s Formula for cyclic quadrilaterals. One man from this country left four notebooks of unproven results upon his untimely death in 1920 after being discovered by, and collaborating with, G.H. Hardy. For the point, name this home country of Srinivasa Ramanujan.", "answer": "Republic of<b> India</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}], "bonuses": []}